Cultists are the backbone of every civilization which worships the ancient gods.  They construct buildings without disturbing the business of townsfolk, they can be easily trained in bulk and, as they exist to be sacrificed, they do not fear death.

Cultists are often found on the front lines, constructing military buildings or erecting their strange black towers, and do so fearlessly.  After all, when death comes for you, why not welcome it and offer yourself to the gods? 

"When the men of K’n-yan discovered the red-litten world and deciphered its strange manuscripts, they took over the Tsathoggua cult and brought all the frightful toad images up to the land of blue light—housing them in shrines of Yoth-quarried basalt like the one Zamacona now saw. The cult flourished until it almost rivalled the ancient cults of Yig and Tulu, and one branch of the race even took it to the outer world, where the smallest of the images eventually found a shrine at Olathoë, in the land of Lomar near the earth’s north pole. It was rumoured that this outer-world cult survived even after the great ice-sheet and the hairy Gnophkehs destroyed Lomar, but of such matters not much was definitely known in K’n-yan. In that world of blue light the cult came to an abrupt end, even though the name of Tsath was suffered to remain."