The Form of Blood is a formless spawn hatchling living inside a bloated, decaying corpse. In a moment, it will explode, releasing a burst of acid. Two will kill a villager instantly. 

"What unimaginable horror of protoplastic life, what loathly spawn of the primordial slime had come forth to confront us, we did not pause to consider or conjecture. The monstrosity was too awful to permit of even a brief contemplation; also, its intentions were too plainly hostile, and it gave evidence of anthropophagic inclinations; for it slithered toward us with an unbelievable speed and celerity of motion, opening as it came a toothless mouth of amazing capacity."