Age -- 795
Homeland -- Aeaea
Occupation -- Sorceress

Circe was a daughter of Perse and the sun god, Helios. She is renown for her encounter with Odysseus and for her knowledge of magic and poisonous herbs. While she imprisoned Odysseus and his men for many years, she later purified the Argonauts for the murder of Apsyrtus. 

Odysseus and Circe bore several children, among them Telegonus. According to some myths, Telegonus later tracked down Odysseus, but killed him with a spear made of a stingray spine before recognizing his own father. Odysseus' body was returned to Aeaea to be buried.