An Invoker refreshes a god power. Some are expensive, some are cheap, but all can be trained as many times as one desires.

Invokers are raised from birth to be the ideal sacrifice to a particular god, and aside from Nyarlathotep, all Eldritch gods are happy to provide more of their power in exchange for such a good offering.

The age that the Invoker is sacrificed varies, of course, but most lie between 6 and 18. 

"I always felt bad for the kids who got sacrified for Maws. Here you and I are, groomed for The End itself, and these poor bastards get turned in for just fifty wood!"