The library is the place where all divine technologies and rituals are researched.  Making one is essential, as not only do the eldritch gods offer great boons to those who worship them, but also for the rituals to unleash their true power upon the world.

In particular, libraries offer the technology True Craftsmen, which allow for the construction of Altars: the next step in favor economy for those whose gods are only appeased with the blood of their worshipers.