Shoggoths are perhaps the most iconic and feared Eldritch myth unit, and with good reason. Their attacks are incredibly powerful, they heal rapidly when attacking, and they may hurl human units with unearthly force. Shoggoths are shapeshifting masses of black sludge, commonly covered in mouths and tentacles and filled with vile organs 

Shoggoths were created as a slave race for the Elder Things, but they rebelled against their cruel masters and drove them to extinction. Now, Shoggoths reside in the dark and deep places, answering the call of the fools that would dare call upon then.

"Formless protoplasm able to mock and reflect all forms and organs and processes - viscous agglutinations of bubbling cells - rubbery fifteen-foot spheroids infinitely plastic and ductile - slaves of suggestion, builders of cities - more and more sullen, more and more intelligent, more and more amphibious, more and more imitative! Great God! What madness made even those blasphemous Old Ones willing to use and carve such things?"