At the Temple you may build mythological units and research improvements that require the Favor of the gods to be implemented. Greeks may pray at their Temples to gain Favor.

Most early civilizations invested considerable wealth in their religious life, including the construction of temples or places where rites and ceremonies were conducted, where religious leaders were trained, and where beliefs were refined and passed on. Temples were often dedicated to one or more gods and acted as points of communication between humans and deities. At the Temple, believers might petition the gods for help and offer prayer, tribute or sacrifices to improve the reception of pleas. Temples were often magnificent buildings that overshadowed anything else in a city.