Voices are the primary heros of the Eldritch civilization. Each god has a voice, and as the age of the god increases, so does its Voices' power and cost.  Each voice has a special ability, and has both a ranged and melee attack. You can train more of each at one time by researching a line of technologies at the temple.

"On the following day Carter walked up the Street of the Pillars to the turquoise temple and talked with the high-priest. Though Nath-Horthath is chiefly worshipped in Celephaïs, all the Great Ones are mentioned in diurnal prayers; and the priest was reasonably versed in their moods. Like Atal in distant Ulthar, he strongly advised against any attempt to see them; declaring that they are testy and capricious, and subject to strange protection from the mindless Other Gods from Outside, whose soul and messenger is the crawling chaos Nyarlathotep. "