The Voormis are three-toed, umber-colored, fur-covered humanoids. Their voices are like the howling of gods, though they have learned the benefits of silence in the centuries and millenia since their civilization's destruction. 

"Now the Voormis had, from their remotest origins, considered themselves the chosen minions of Tsathoggua, the sole deity whose worship they celebrated. And Tsathoggua was an earth elemental ranged in perpetual and unrelenting enmity against the Rhan-Tegoth and all his kind, who were commonly accounted elementals of the air, and were objects of contempt to those of the Old Ones, like Tsathoggua, who abominated the airy emptiness above the world and by preference wallowed in darksome and subterranean lairs."